{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which one of the following is incombustible ?", "opta": "H2", "optb": "CCl4", "optc": "C2H2", "optd": "S", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The softness or hardness of a grinding wheel depends upon the type & amount of bonding material used. For general purpose cutter grinding __________ grinding wheel is normally used.", "opta": "hard", "optb": "soft", "optc": "silicon carbide", "optd": "aluminium oxide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tin based white metals are used, where bearings are subjected to", "opta": "high pressure & load.", "optb": "low pressure & load.", "optc": "high temperature.", "optd": "large surface wear.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Friction factor for fluid flow in pipe does not depend upon the", "opta": "pipe length.", "optb": "pipe roughness.", "optc": "fluid density & viscosity.", "optd": "mass flow rate of fluid.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All of the following alloying elements of steel increases hardness but sacrifice ductility, except", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "vanadium", "optc": "molybdenum", "optd": "chromium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The following type of bonding is strongly directional in solids.", "opta": "Vander Waal's", "optb": "Ionic", "optc": "Metallic", "optd": "Covalant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fog is an example of colloidal system of", "opta": "solid dispersed in gas.", "optb": "solid dispersed in liquid.", "optc": "liquid dispersed in gas.", "optd": "gas dispersed in liquid.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chromium molybdenum steel can not be welded using __________ welding.", "opta": "thermit", "optb": "electrical resistance", "optc": "oxy-acetylene", "optd": "any of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Speisses is a mixture of the following:", "opta": "Arsenides of heavy metals.", "optb": "Antimonides of heavy metals.", "optc": "Arsenides & antimonides of heavy metals.", "optd": "Iron, cobalt and nickel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Auto collimator is used to check", "opta": "flatness", "optb": "angle", "optc": "rotor balancing", "optd": "roughness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In troposphere (the weather domain), the temperature 't' at height 'h' above the sea level in metres is given by (where, temperature at sea level is 15\u00b0C and t is in \u00b0C.)", "opta": "t = 15 - 0.0065 h", "optb": "t = 15 + 0.0065 h", "optc": "t = 0.0035 h - 15", "optd": "t = 15 - 0.0035 h", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A high pressure boiler generates steam at a pressure greater than __________ kg/cm2 .", "opta": "10", "optb": "30", "optc": "50", "optd": "80", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Evaporative cooling process employs a combination of cooling and humidification in which the", "opta": "sensible heat is added.", "optb": "sensible heat is removed and the latent heat is added.", "optc": "latent heat is removed.", "optd": "sensible heat is added and latent heat is removed.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an explosive ?", "opta": "TNT", "optb": "CMC", "optc": "RDX", "optd": "Lead azide", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maxwell's thermodynamic relations applies to the", "opta": "chemical systems in equilibrium.", "optb": "mechanical systems in equilibrium.", "optc": "irreversible thermodynamic processes.", "optd": "reversible thermodynamic processes.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Annealing ofwhite cast iron produces __________ iron.", "opta": "grey", "optb": "nodular", "optc": "malleable", "optd": "spheroidal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resistance of an electrical conductor is proportional to its (where, l = length and A = cross-sectional area of the conductor)", "opta": "A", "optb": "l", "optc": "A2", "optd": "both 'a' & 'b'", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A solar cell converts the sunlight directly into __________ energy.", "opta": "thermal", "optb": "electrical", "optc": "mechanical", "optd": "chemical", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a nuclear reactor produces more fissile nuclear fuel than it consumes, then it is called a __________ reactor.", "opta": "critical", "optb": "breeder", "optc": "fertile", "optd": "heterogenous", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wrought iron is never shaped by", "opta": "casting", "optb": "cold working", "optc": "forging", "optd": "welding", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Powder metallurgy process does not make metal powder by", "opta": "atomisation", "optb": "grinding/milling", "optc": "hammering", "optd": "electrolytic deposition", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the blast furnace, incorporation of water vapour in the blast gives the following effect.", "opta": "Increases the reducing potential of the gas.", "optb": "Increases the flame temperature.", "optc": "No significant change occurs.", "optd": "Increases the hydrogen content in the metal.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "A ferromagnetic material becomes paramagnetic above the 'Curie temperature'.", "optb": "Permanent magnets are made of hard materials, whereas electromagnets require soft magnetic materials.", "optc": "Soft magnetic materials (e.g., pure iron) have higher permeability and low hysterisis loss and coercive forces.", "optd": "Tungsten steel and alnico are not hard magnetic materials.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The usual energy consumption in electric arc furnace steel making is __________ KWh/ton of steel.", "opta": "60 - 100", "optb": "400 - 700", "optc": "1200 -1500", "optd": "2000 - 2300", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum permissible air velocity in pipelines is about __________ metre/second.", "opta": "5", "optb": "10", "optc": "20", "optd": "40", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Area under the stress-strain curve upto the __________ is referred to as the modulus of resilience.", "opta": "yield strength", "optb": "elastic limit", "optc": "proportional limit", "optd": "maximum point", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is the hardest oxide and is hence used where high wear resistance at high temperature is required.", "opta": "Beryllia", "optb": "Zirconia", "optc": "Alumina", "optd": "Magnesia", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Titanium alloys are welded using the Following process:", "opta": "TIG welding.", "optb": "Submerged arc welding.", "optc": "Butt welding.", "optd": "Electron beam welding.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An alloy of Fe - 0.4 % C is", "opta": "cast iron.", "optb": "hypo-eutectoid steel.", "optc": "hyper-eutectoid steel.", "optd": "eutectoid steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material in which the atoms are arranged regularly in some directions but not in others, is termed as 'mesomorphous material'; an example of which is", "opta": "lead", "optb": "glass", "optc": "mica", "optd": "silver", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In extrusion of metals, which of the following statement is true ?", "opta": "speed of the extruded material is same as that of ram speed.", "optb": "Redundant work is a function of the die angle.", "optc": "Relative motion between the billet surface and the container wall is always present.", "optd": "Hollow ram is used for indirect extrusion.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nuclear fission of one atom of uranium-235 produces the energy equivalent to about __________ MeV.", "opta": "20", "optb": "200", "optc": "500", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following parameters is not responsible for the heat loss from a hot steam carrying bare pipe surface located in a room without fans ?", "opta": "Emissivity of pipe surface.", "optb": "Diameter & length of the pipe.", "optc": "Temperature of hot pipe surface & that of air in the room.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Machinability of hard alloys and tool steels is improved by", "opta": "spherodising", "optb": "annealing", "optc": "tempering", "optd": "normalising", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transformation range for ferrous material is the temperature interval during which __________ is formed during its heating.", "opta": "cementite", "optb": "austenite", "optc": "martensite", "optd": "pearlite", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum amount of thermal radiation is emitted at all wavelengths at any specified temperature by a/an __________ body.", "opta": "grey", "optb": "black", "optc": "opaque", "optd": "white", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In condensers used in thermal power plants, steam is normally used in shell side and cooling water on the tube side, because of the reason that", "opta": "compared to the mass flow rate of cooling water, the rate of condensation of steam is invariably smaller.", "optb": "maintaining vacuum on tube side is more difficult than that on the shell side.", "optc": "water velocity can be increased conveniently to increase the overall heat transfer co-efficient because of its lower specific volume compared to steam.", "optd": "condenser can act as a storage unit for condensed steam.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cobalt - 60 is used as a source of __________ in medical therapy & industrial radiography.", "opta": "X-rays", "optb": "\u03b3-rays", "optc": "\u03b1-rays", "optd": "\u03b2-rays", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absolute zero pressure can be attained at a temperature of", "opta": "0\u00b0C", "optb": "50\u00b0K", "optc": "0\u00b0R", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The product out from a cupola is called", "opta": "wrought iron", "optb": "pig iron", "optc": "cast iron", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nusselt number is related to Grashoff number (Gr) in turbulent & laminar flow respectively, in respect of free convection over a vertical flat plate as", "opta": "Gr0.25, Gr", "optb": "Gr0.25, Gr0.33", "optc": "Gr, Gr0.25", "optd": "Gr0.33, Gr0.25", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the demand for an item is trebled and the order cost is reduced to one third, then the economic order quantity", "opta": "is trebled.", "optb": "remains unchanged.", "optc": "decreases by a factor of 3.", "optd": "decreases by a factor of 1/3.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Copper deposits are found in India at the following location:", "opta": "Kudremukh", "optb": "Kolar", "optc": "Khetri", "optd": "Ramagundam", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electrical conductivities of semi-conductors are of the order of __________ ohm/cm.", "opta": "10-3", "optb": "103", "optc": "10-15", "optd": "l015", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Corrosion of metals can not be prevented by its", "opta": "tempering", "optb": "chromising", "optc": "aluminising", "optd": "alloying", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transition from laminar to turbulent zone in free convection heat transfer is governed by the critical value of", "opta": "Grashoff number.", "optb": "Grashoff number & Reynolds number.", "optc": "Reynolds number.", "optd": "Grashoff number & Prandtl number.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most economical channel section for the fluid flow is the one for which the discharge is maximum for a given cross-sectional area. Vertical velocity distribution in an open channel for laminar flow can be assumed to be", "opta": "parabolic", "optb": "hyperbolic", "optc": "straight line", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Energy of the sun arises mainly from __________ reactions.", "opta": "fusion", "optb": "fission", "optc": "combustion", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following fastening devices has a head at one end and a nut fitted to the other ?", "opta": "Bolt", "optb": "Stud", "optc": "Top bolt", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sudden fall of atmospheric pressure by a large amount is an indication of the", "opta": "rain", "optb": "cold wave", "optc": "storm", "optd": "fair weather", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}